<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the famous &amp; renowmed [sic] victorie latelie atchieued by the counte Maurice of Nassau, neere to Newport in Flaunders against the arch-duke Albertus with the names of such noblemen &amp; others of acount, as haue bin eyther slaine or taken prisoners in this seruice late-done and y [sic] performed. Truly translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113158</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848397</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the famous &amp; renowmed [sic] victorie latelie atchieued by the counte Maurice of Nassau, neere to Newport in Flaunders against the arch-duke Albertus with the names of such noblemen &amp; others of acount, as haue bin eyther slaine or taken prisoners in this seruice late-done and y [sic] performed. Truly translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Prince of Orange, 1567-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ralph Blower, for C. B[urby],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1600]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date and publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B¹ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  history --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True Relation of the famous &amp; renowmed Victorie latelie atchieued by the Counte Maurice of Naſſau, neere to Newport in Flaunders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arch-Duke ALBERTVS: with the names of ſuch noblemen &amp; others of account, as haue bin ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlaine or taken Priſoners in this ſeruice late-done and y performed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Truly tranſlated out of the Duch copie.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by Ralph Blower, for C. B.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13487:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13487:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A TRVE RELATION of the late proceadings of the States Armie in Flaunders, and of the late ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice done and performed by them againſt the Spanniardes, the two and twentith of Iune laſt paſt. 1600.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Tweluth of Iune laſt paſt, (after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Englande) the States of the lowe Cuntries landed in Flaunders, néere to a place called <hi>Burfleete,</hi> and in Nine dayes march, they came from thence to <hi>Oſtende:</hi> where after the taking of certaine Sconces, the <hi>Count Maurice</hi> laide ſiege, to the Towne of <hi>Newport,</hi> purpoſing to fortifie him ſelfe in ſuch ſort, as not to be eaſily remoued: howbeit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch was the great care and dilligence of the Enemie to preuent them, as the Arch-Duke came himſelfe in perſon to giue them Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile. But the ſuddaine and ſpeadie comming of the Enemie cauſed the States Armie (not being well ſetled in the ſiege) to remoue thence, and to encounter the Enemie, who then marched towardes them with great furie, they being the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incouraged thereto, by reaſon of an euerthrow giuen to two Thowſande Scots (being the States men of warre) the ſame morning, which Scottes were vnder the Conducte or leading of the <hi>Count ERNESTVS,</hi> who was ſent before to
<pb facs="tcp:13487:3"/>preuent the paſſage of the Enemie by the way.</p>
            <p>After this, both the Armies being ordred &amp; placed in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile array, and each of them within ſight of other: they pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a while who ſhould beginne the fight, or giue the firſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet: at length the Enemie impatient of delayes, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with the former victorie obtained againſt the Scots, advaunced themſelues forwardes, diſplaide their Enſignes, and gaue the Charge: which was entertained with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſollution on the Sates ſide, as they were forced to a retreat, and were purſued till they had gayned ſome places of aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Their Horſes chardging the States men in flancke, whoſe ſecondes fayling them, they were inforced to retire: But making preſently a ſtande, they forced the Enemy to a ſecond Retreat, which was then ſo hottely followed by the States men, and with ſuch great courage and reſollution, that they had the aduauntage in ſlaughtering and killing of the Enemie, from the Hauen of <hi>Newport,</hi> to the walles of <hi>Oſtende.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Battaile, the Engliſhmen had the Van-guarde, commaunded by Sir <hi>Fraunces Vere</hi> and his Brother.</p>
            <p>The Honor of the Victorie that day, was whollie aſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the Engliſh-men.</p>
            <p>In this fight were ſlaine, fiue Engliſh Captaines, beſides other Captaines and Officers that were hurt, Sir <hi>Fraunces Vere</hi> himſelfe was hurt in the Legge and Thighes, and my <hi>Lorde Gray</hi> was hurt in the face with a Sworde.</p>
            <p>Of the States men (of all ſortes) there were ſlaine, more then two Thouſande, and as many more ſore hurt and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly wounded.</p>
            <p>Of the Enemies parte, it is crediblie reported, that there was aboue foure thouſande ſlaine, and aboue a thouſande ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners, beſides many that were hurt and wounded.</p>
            <p>The Enemies Armie conſiſted as it was reported in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:13487:3"/>or Eight Thouſande footemen, and Seauentéene Cornets of Horſemen, and were devided into thrée ſquadrons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt being Spaniardes, and were conducted by <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois de Villeers, Don Iaſper de Sapena,</hi> and <hi>Ieronimo denau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt two were taken Priſoners, &amp; the thirde of them is not as yet hearde of.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde ſquadron were Wallons, and were conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one <hi>La Berlotte Don Alfonſo</hi> and <hi>Boſtock,</hi> Nephew to ſir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> whereof <hi>La Berlot</hi> and <hi>Boſtock</hi> were both ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The Thirde Squadron were Flemminges, and were vnder the commaunde of one <hi>Backwrie,</hi> who was alſo ſlaine at that time.</p>
            <p>The Admirall of <hi>Aragon</hi> is taken Priſoner, and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely thought that Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> is ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The Spanniardes loſt their Ordinances, (being ſome Eight great pieces in the whole) and the Arch-Duke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe loſt all his own Plate and Baggage.</p>
            <p>The fighte continued from one of the Clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till fiue in the after Noone of the ſame day.</p>
            <p>The Spaniardes loſt in this ſeruice, aboue an hundred Enſignes, as is moſt certainly knowne.</p>
            <p>The Arch-Duke himſelfe fled into <hi>Bridges,</hi> and ſo eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away very bardely, he being ſomewhat hurt as it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>The States Armie is now before <hi>Newport,</hi> and the place as it is thought, rendred vp to the States before this time.</p>
            <div type="list">
               <pb facs="tcp:13487:4"/>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ The Names of the fiue Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Captaines that then were ſlaine, were theſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine Yaxley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine Hunnywoode.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine Parden.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine Terret.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine Paxroy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="lists">
               <pb facs="tcp:13487:4"/>
               <p>The names of ſuch Noblemen and Commaunders of the Enemie, as then were either taken or ſlaine by the <hi>Counte Maurice</hi> and his forces.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Priſoners of account taken.</head>
                  <item>Don Franciſco de Mendoſa, Marques of Quadelles, and great Admirall of ARRAGON.</item>
                  <item>The Counte of Salins.</item>
                  <item>The Counte de la Fiere.</item>
                  <item>Don Lewis de Valaſco.</item>
                  <item>Don Charles de Sapina.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The Names of ſuch as were ſlaine in the Conflict.</head>
                  <item>The Count of Bauquoy.</item>
                  <item>The Count Frederick Vanden Bergh.</item>
                  <item>Don Ambroſio de Adrians.</item>
                  <item>Don Iohn de Rymans, Commaunder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Flemmiſh Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Parlotte commaunder of the Wallons.</item>
                  <item>Mounſieur Freſyne.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13487:5"/>
                  <item>The Gouernour of Dunkerke.</item>
                  <item>The Traitour William Stanley.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Of the Arch-Duke <hi>ALBERTVS.</hi> and of the Duke of <hi>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> there is no certaintie as yet, whether they be dead or aliue.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, all the Enſignes and Banners that were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Enemie in this ſeruice were brought into the Tent of his Excellencie, and his Souldiers were mightely enriched by the Spoyle.</p>
               <p>The Arch-Ducheſſe her ſelfe trauailed with the Campe, vntill ſhe came to the Cittie of <hi>Bridges</hi> in Flaunders, where ſhe then left them.</p>
               <p>It is ſince reported by ſome, that the Arch-Duke is yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and that there are come vnto him to the number of ſix Thouſande freſh Souldiers, (taken vp in <hi>Artois,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nault</hi>) and are vnder the conduct of the Duke of <hi>Arſchot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo it is reported for certainetie, that there are <hi>3000</hi> freſh men taken out of the lande of <hi>Luick,</hi> and that they are with all ſpeade marching to the Campe of his Excellencie, the Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:13487:5"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
